<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Earl of Maclesfeld's case</title>
            <author>Macclesfield, Charles Gerard, Earl of, 1659?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697-1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E76</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895607</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2353:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Earl of Maclesfeld's case</title>
                  <author>Macclesfield, Charles Gerard, Earl of, 1659?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The Earl of Macclesfield's case for divorcing his wife Anne, Countess of Macclesfield; the divorce received the royal assent on 2nd April 1698.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Macclesfield, Charles Gerard, --  Earl of, 1659?-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brett, Anne, d. 1753 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trials (Divorce) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153188:1"/>
            <head>THE Earl of Maclesfeld's Caſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE preſent Earl of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> having early grounds not to recal his Lady from that ſtate of Separation, which ſhe choſe, by leaving his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe in her Husband's abſence, without his privity; thought himſelf the leſs concerned in her way of living, ſince ſhe had enough to maintain her ſelf with Credit, her Mother being permitted to receive for her 300 <hi>l.</hi> a year, which was by the Marriage-Settlement provided for her particular <hi>Maintenance and Expences:</hi> Nor would he have required an Account of 200 <hi>l.</hi> a year more, which the Mother received during the whole time of the Separation; if he had not too juſt occaſion to be provoked at the Daughter's Conduct, which, without the Interpoſition of the Legiſlative Power, muſt fix a laſting Burthen and Diſhonour upon his Family.</p>
            <p>About a Year and half ſince, he had certain Information of her being delivered of a Female Child, the Death of which, before he had heard any thing of it, with the belief that this might be a ſufficient warning againſt Liberties which carried ſuch viſible Effects with them, with-held him from attempting publick Satisfaction. After this there being a Treaty concerning the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears of the 200 <hi>l.</hi> a year due to the Earl, at the Interceſſion of her Siſter, the Lady <hi>Brownlow,</hi> who undertook that her Mother and ſhe as Executrixes to Sir <hi>Richard Maſon,</hi> would pay him 1000 <hi>l.</hi> and Indemnify him againſt his Lady's Debts; and that ſhe would be accountable for her Siſter's Conduct, if ſhe might be permitted to live with her; Articles were prepared to this end by their Sollicitor, and conſented to by the Earl, with ſome Alterations; but it was particularly provided and agreed, that ſhe ſhould live ſeparate from him, and have the whole 500 <hi>l.</hi> a Year, which the Earl would have allowed in the Account from the Death of his Father. The Execution of this ſeemed to be delayed only for the raiſing 500 <hi>l.</hi> part of the 1000 <hi>l.</hi> But the certain Intelligence which the Earl had of her being a Second time with Child during her Elopement, broke off all Treaties of that kind, and obliged him to apply himſelf to the Siſter, the Lady <hi>Brownlow,</hi> who had undertaken for her Conduct; therefore he thought he had the greater reaſon to importune the Siſter more than once, that ſhe might be produced to ſuch Ladies as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhe knew not where her Siſter was, but begged of him not to expoſe her; and ſoon after ſent a Letter to one who had been with his Lordſhip when he made that Demand; which Letter imported the indemnifying him from any Child begotten on her Siſter; notwithſtanding which, their Agents and Friends induſtriouſly ſpread a Report, That the Earl had been ſurprized into a private Meeting with his Lady, at which time he got her with Child; and that a Ring and Bracelet which he then parted with, would evidence who was the Father: And yet this Story was not contrived well enough to colour the two baſe Births.</p>
            <p>The full Diſcovery of theſe happened too late within the laſt Seſſions of this Parliament, for the Earl then to bring his Proofs thither.</p>
            <p>Wherefore for perpetuating the Teſtimony of the Witneſſes, and to give full Opportunity to his Lady to offer what ſhe could for the clearing her ſelf, he in<note n="a" place="margin">26. <hi>Apr.</hi> 97. Proceſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd with Certificate, that ſhe could not be found to be perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſerved.</note> 
               <hi>April</hi> 1697. commenced his Suit in the Spiritual Court for ſuch a Divorce as may be given by that Law; but he was not in the leaſt ſurprized to find all the confirmation imaginable to his Proofs of her Adultery, by the groſs and notorious Delays which ſhe ſought, ſtanding out a<note n="b" place="margin">14 <hi>May</hi> 97. Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed.</note> Sentence of Excommunication; beſides other Delays which ſhe uſed. But when ſhe<note n="c" place="margin">31 <hi>May</hi> 97.</note> appeared to take off her Excommunication, ſhe was more wary than to deny the Charge in the Libel upon Oath, ſeeming doubtful whether ſhe had not beſt confeſs a Child, and lay it upon the Earl, as begotten by him; but that ſhe might govern her ſelf according to what ſhe might after be adviſed, ſhe only in general<note n="d" place="margin">4. <hi>June</hi> 97.</note> conteſted the Suit, and the Earl was admitted to produce his Witneſſes, ſome of which were ſworn: But there being others, to whom ſhe had appeared only in diſguiſe, without her true Name, after a full hearing by Doctors on both Sides, the Dean of the Arches<note n="e" place="margin">10 <hi>June</hi> 97.</note> decreed, That ſhe ſhould be confronted by thoſe Witneſſes; but ſhe having a while ſtood in contempt,<note n="f" place="margin">24 <hi>June</hi> 97.</note> the 24th of <hi>June</hi> laſt, pretended to appeal to the Delegates from this Sentence, as a Grievance; but no Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Appeal having been taken out, or due notice given of ſo much as a Petition for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the Earl proceeded in the Spiritual Court to have his Witneſſes examined, during whoſe Examination, ſhe a ſecond time petitioned for a Commiſſion, complaining of this as a farther Grievance, and had a <hi>fiat</hi> for a Commiſſion, which reſting without any Inhibition to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> he went on with his Proofs;<note place="margin">2. <hi>July</hi> 97.</note> the ſubſtance of which is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dinah Alſop,</hi> who lived with the Lady as her Maid or Woman, ſwears, That in <hi>April</hi> or <hi>May</hi> 1695.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> or <hi>May</hi> 95.</note> ſhe by her Lady's Order brought a ſtrange Gentleman in the Evening to her Bedchamber at her Siſter the Lady <hi>Brownlow</hi>'s Houſe in Town, where he continued till 3 the next Morning, the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber Door being lock'd after him all that time from whence ſhe let him out by the Back door: that at another time he ſtaid from Evening till Eleven or Twelve, and that the ſame Perſon came to her in the Country, where Mrs. <hi>Alſop</hi> firſt knew his Name; That in <hi>June,</hi> 95.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>June</hi> 95.</note> the Lady declared to Mrs. <hi>Alſop,</hi> that <hi>ſhe had been unfortunate, and was with Child,</hi> and went to a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſe in <hi>Queenſtreet</hi> in <hi>Piccadilly,</hi> from whence ſhe ſent Mrs. <hi>Alſop</hi> for Mrs. <hi>Richardſon,</hi> the Midwife, with whom ſhe diſcourſed in a Mask: That the Midwife being of opinion ſhe would go a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153188:2"/>month longer, ſhe returned to her Siſter the Lady <hi>Brownlow</hi>'s Houſe in the Country, from whence ſhe came back again to <hi>Piccadilly, July</hi> 10.95. and was brought to Bed of a Female Child, <hi>July</hi> 11. at Two in the Morning,<note place="margin">10. <hi>July</hi> 95. 11. <hi>July</hi> 95.</note> having a Mask on for themoſt of the time, no other Perſon being preſent, but the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Alſop,</hi> the Midwife, and Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> the Nurſe; That the Child was chriſtned the ſame Day by the Name of <hi>Ann,</hi> as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> informed her: That the Lady declared to Mrs. <hi>Alſop,</hi> That no body but ſhe knew the Name of the Father. That within Six Days after being delivered, ſhe removed to her Siſter's Houſe in Town, which occaſioned a Swelling in her Leg and Thigh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 95.</note> for which ſhe went to the <hi>Bath</hi> at the latter end of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> But before that, Mrs. <hi>Alſop</hi> from her Lady gave Nurſe <hi>Pheaſant</hi> a Guinea to take Care of the Child: And after returning from the <hi>Bath,</hi> went twice with the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Stileman</hi>'s, where the Counteſs ſpoke with Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant.</hi> That the Child was carried to a Place near <hi>Epping-Foreſt;</hi> and as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> ſaid, removed by her to Mrs. <hi>Mountaine</hi>'s at <hi>Chelſea,</hi> whither Mrs. <hi>Alſop</hi> went twice with the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> to ſee the Child, and at each Time ſhe gave the Nurſe Five Shillings. That Mrs. <hi>Alſop</hi> finding her Lady a Second Time with Child, refuſed to live with her, and threatned to diſcover in what Condition ſhe was: To prevent which, the Lady <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> gave her Twenty Guineas in hand, and promiſed her Five Pound a Year to live with her own Siſter at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of which ſhe ſent her the firſt Quarter's Wages.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Richardſon</hi> the Midwife Swears, That in the Summer 1695, ſhe was fetched to a Private Houſe in <hi>Queenſtreet</hi> in <hi>Piccadilly,</hi> where a Gentlewoman with Child diſcourſed her with a Mask on; and that about a Fortnight or Month after, ſhe at the ſame place delivered the ſame Gentlewoman, who all the while kept on her Mask, or had her Face ſo ſhaded with an Handkerchief, or ſomething elſe, that ſhe did not ſee it, and that no Body beſides was preſent, but the Nurſe and another Woman who attended on her.</p>
            <p>The Curat of St. <hi>James</hi>'s proves,<note place="margin">11 <hi>July.</hi> 95.</note> That the 11th of <hi>July</hi> 1695, a Child was Chriſtned by the Name of <hi>Anne:</hi> which by the Circumſtances <hi>he ſuſpected to be a Baſe Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Mountaine</hi> of <hi>Chelſey</hi> Swears, That in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1695, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her ſhe wanted a Nurſe for a Child,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 95.</note> which was then at <hi>Walthamſtow,</hi> that the Names of the Parents were to be kept private; that the <hi>Friday</hi> following ſhe went to Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> at Mrs. <hi>Stilemans</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> and that ſhe, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> one Mrs. <hi>Stacy,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Stileman,</hi> went together in a Coach to <hi>Walthamſtow,</hi> from whence they fetched the Child, and carried it to her Houſe at <hi>Chelſea,</hi> where ſhe nurſed it about Seven Months: that Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> frequently ſaw the Child, and told her the <hi>Mother was a Counteſs,</hi> and that the Mother was at the <hi>Bath,</hi> but enjoined her ſecrecy: that a Lady, who ſeemed very fond of the Child, and whom ſhe then believed to be the Mother, came Twice to ſee it, attended by one <hi>Dinah Alſop,</hi> whom ſhe knew in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Service, and as ſhe has been told, Lived with the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld,</hi> and each time gave her Five Shillings: That upon her deſcribing to Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> what ſort of Perſon had been to ſee the Child, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her ſhe was the Mother: and that ſhe was ſometimes paid for Nurſing by Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> ſometimes by another.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Stileman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Aug.</hi> 95.</note> Jun. Swears, That Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> who lived at her Mother's in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> was Abſent for 5 Weeks, about <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1695. and informed her, that ſhe had Attended a Lady, who in that <hi>July</hi> was brought to Bed by Mrs. <hi>Richardſon</hi> (who had Twenty Guineas) of a Female Child in <hi>Queenſtreet</hi> in <hi>Piccadilly;</hi> that one <hi>Dinah</hi> was her Maid or Woman, with whom Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> deſired her to ſpeak, if ſhe call'd in her Abſence: and that <hi>Dinah Alſop</hi> produced as a Witneſs in the Cauſe, is the Woman who Once or Twice called there with a Lady in a Mask in the Summer, 1695.</p>
            <p>That ſhe, the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Stileman,</hi> in Company with Mrs. <hi>Mountaine</hi> a Nurſe of <hi>Chelſea,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Stacy,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> fetch'd a Child from Nurſe at <hi>Walthamſtow,</hi> and carried it to Mrs. <hi>Mountaine</hi>'s at <hi>Chelſea;</hi> this, as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her, was the Child of which the Lady was Delivered in <hi>Queenſtreet,</hi> and that the Lady was a Counteſs. That Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> by <hi>Dinah,</hi> received a Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea from the Lady to look after the Child in her abſence at the <hi>Bath.</hi> And that ſhe, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Mountaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>March,</hi> 95/6.</note> and another, were at the Child's Funeral at <hi>Chelſea,</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> 1695/6.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Stileman,</hi> the Mother, agrees in the time of Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi>'s abſence from her Houſe; Swears, That ſhe declared ſhe had been Waiting on a Counteſs, that Mrs. <hi>Richardſon</hi> had Delivered her, as before-mentioned; that Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her, the Counteſs had no Father Alive, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Lived with her Mother, ſometimes with her Siſter; that ſhe went Once or Twice with Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> to <hi>Chelſea</hi> to ſee the Child, which Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her was the Counteſs's Child whom ſhe nurſed in <hi>Queenſtreet</hi> in <hi>Piccadilly,</hi> but the Child and the Delivery muſt be kept Private.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Dinah Alſop,</hi> who as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her was that Counteſs's Woman, came often to her Houſe, Once or Twice with a Lady Masked, who, as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> ſaid, was the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, and brought a Guinea from her when ſhe was going to the <hi>Bath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it appears, That without Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> there was full Proof, and an evident concurrence of Circumſtances which put it beyond queſtion, That the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> had been Clandeſtinely Delivered of a Female Child, while ſhe continued Separate from her Husband, and had private Converſation and Opportunities with other Men.</p>
            <p>All the Evidences both of this, and as will afterwards appear, of another Baſe Birth, Center in Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant;</hi> as the Principal Party truſted with the Lady's Secrets; ſhe therefore was Cited to give Evidence of what ſhe knew, but was by the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi>'s Agents, in whoſe Hands ſhe was, prevailed upon, after ſervice of the Citation, to Abſent her ſelf from the uſual place of her Abode; and was ſo backward from coming to give Evidence, that ſhe ſtood out Sentence of Excommunication: after which the Earl, having juſt reaſon to apprehend ſhe would go beyond Sea, obtained a <hi>ne exeat Regnum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With which ſhe being ſerved in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> whither the Lady's Agents had carried her, choſe Voluntarily to Confeſs what ſhe knew, and upon Examination declared, That in the beginning of <hi>July</hi> 1695,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>July,</hi> 95. 10 <hi>July,</hi> 95.</note> ſhe was employed by a certain Perſon to attend a Gentlewoman at her Lying in; that about the Tenth of <hi>July,</hi> ſhe, by Order of that Gentlewoman, went for Mrs. <hi>Richardſon</hi> the Midwife, who Delivered the Party of a Female Child about Three the next Morning, at an Houſe in <hi>Queenſtreet, Piccadilly,</hi> where no Body was preſent beſides her, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153188:3"/>Midwife, and Mrs. <hi>Dinah Alſop;</hi> that for the greateſt par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t the time the Lady was in her Labour, ſhe had her Mask on, which fell off in the extremity of the Pain, when ſhe hid her Head in Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi>'s Boſom. That the Child was Chriſtned the ſame Day, by the Name of <hi>Anne;</hi> that the Gentlewoman ſtaid at the Houſe but Six Days after being Delivered; that ſhe had told her this was her Firſt Child, but <hi>ſhe had Miſcarried once before.</hi> She confirms all the other Circumſtances about the Nurſing of the Child, the Gentlewoman's coming to her Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with <hi>Dinah Alſop,</hi> and other Matters Sworn in reference to her; and ſays, that ſhe did ſuſpect the Party ſo Delivered was the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld,</hi> becauſe of the Superſcription of a Letter which ſhe had ſeen, and the Caution given her by a certain Perſon when ſhe mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch her Suſpition.</p>
            <p>This is but the Subſtance of the Proof of the <hi>Counteſs</hi>'s having had a Daughter: It is no leſs clear that this was not ſufficient Warning to her, but ſhe ventured for a Son to Inherit the Earl's Eſtate and Honour, though not of his Getting; and accordingly had one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dinah Alſop,</hi> who lived with her as her Maid or Woman, ſwears, That ſhe was a Second Time with Child; and though as much Care was uſed to conceal this as the former, it came to open Light, and gave Occaſion for the more particular enquiring into the Firſt.</p>
            <p>This was not ſo concealed, but Notice came to the Earl of her being with Child. About the latter end of <hi>November,</hi> 1696. he ſent one into the Countrey, to endeavour to ſee in what Condition the <hi>Counteſs</hi> was: He not finding her at her Mother's, went to her Siſter's,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nov.</hi> 96.</note> the Lady <hi>Brownlow,</hi> who ſeemed much ſurprized, and trembled at a Letter only importing an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after the Lady <hi>Maclesfeld;</hi> but declared ſhe did not know where her Siſter was, but ſhould be in <hi>London</hi> next Morning.</p>
            <p>Soon after her coming to Town, the Earl twice applied himſelf to her, as before obſerved; and having no Satisfaction from the Siſter, but rather a Confirmation of what he believed; made all the Enquiry he could, to find where the <hi>Counteſs</hi> was, but heard nothing till after her having a Second Child, of which as it will appear, ſhe was delivered in <hi>January,</hi> 1696/7.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 96/7.</note> by the Name of Madam <hi>Smith,</hi> in <hi>Fox-Court</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Burbridge,</hi> Aſſiſtant to Dr. <hi>Manningham</hi>'s Curate for St. <hi>Andrews Holborn,</hi> and <hi>John Smith,</hi> the Sexton, ſwear, That on the 18th of <hi>January,</hi> a Child was Chriſten'd in <hi>Fox-Court:</hi>
               <note place="margin">18. <hi>Jan.</hi> 96/7.</note> The Clerk proves, That the Child was Entred by the Name of <hi>Richard,</hi> the Son of <hi>John Smith;</hi> and by the Privacy, he ſuppoſed the Child to be a <hi>By-blow or Baſtard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Pegler</hi> ſwears, That on a <hi>Tueſday,</hi> after the 16th of <hi>January,</hi> from the Houſe of Mrs. <hi>Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> (who went by the Name of <hi>Lee</hi> in <hi>Fox-Court</hi>) ſhe took a Male-Child, whoſe Mother was called Madam <hi>Smith.</hi> But it will appear, That as Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> was the Perſon who went by the Name of <hi>Lee,</hi> Madam <hi>Smith</hi> was the Counteſs of <hi>Maclesfeld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Wright</hi> a Midwife, ſwears, That about Two Months before <hi>January,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her to Deliver a Gentlewoman privately married; and told her it was agreed upon ſhe ſhould take an Houſe by the Name of <hi>Lee,</hi> and the Gentlewoman was to be as her Lodger. That about Three or Four Days before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Holborn:</hi> That about Six in the Morning ſhe delivered a Gentlewoman of a Male-Child; Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> one Mrs. <hi>Mathews,</hi> and one <hi>Sarah</hi> a Servant, being preſent. That ſhe did not ſee the Party's Face, nor did in Three Viſits after; and remembers, by recollecting Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, That <hi>Sarah Redhead</hi> was the Servant preſent at the Delivery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sarah Redhead</hi> confirms what is ſworn by Mrs. <hi>Wright;</hi> and adds, That the Gentlewoman ſo delivered, went by the Name of Madam <hi>Smith:</hi> That the Lady was delivered on a <hi>Saturday,</hi> and the <hi>Monday</hi> following the Child was Chriſten'd by the Name of <hi>Richard,</hi> there being then in the Houſe a certain Gentleman, the Miniſter, Clerk, and a Gentleman who often uſed to come at Night, and ſtay till Twelve with the Gentlewoman who was brought to Bed; ſays, ſhe is well aſſured ſhe ſhould know the Gentlewoman, if ſhe ſaw her again; and makes a particular Deſcription of her Perſon: and that Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> uſed to whiſper a Crony of hers, That the Gentlewoman was a Perſon of Quality, and the Child, if a Boy would be a Great Heir.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Stileman</hi> the Elder ſwears, That in <hi>October</hi> 1696. a Lady in a Mask came to Mrs. <hi>Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 96.</note> at her Houſe in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> which Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> declared was the ſame ſhe ſaw delivered in <hi>Queenſtreet, Piccadilly:</hi> That the Lady declared ſhe was with Child again, giving her Ten Shillings, and ordered her to take a Private Houſe for her; that ſhe was a Perſon of Worth: That on the 23d of <hi>October,</hi> ſhe the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Stileman,</hi> at Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi>'s deſire, took a Houſe in <hi>Fox-Court,</hi> and received a Quarter's Rent beforehand of her. That in <hi>January</hi> 1696/7.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 96/7.</note> ſhe went often to that Houſe to one <hi>Sarah Redhead;</hi> and that Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her, The Lady who had been delivered in <hi>Queenſtreet,</hi> was brought to Bed there on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 16th of <hi>January.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16. <hi>Jan.</hi> 96/7.</note> She ſwears, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> told her, that Bitch <hi>Dinah,</hi> who uſed to come with the Lady in the Mask, had betray'd her; that otherwiſe ſhe ſhould have had 100 <hi>l.</hi> and 10 <hi>l.</hi> a Year during Life.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Stileman, Junior,</hi> ſwears, ſhe was informed by Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> That the Lady who was delivered in <hi>Fox-Court</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Wright,</hi> was the ſame whom ſhe had attended at her Lying-in at <hi>Queenſtreet,</hi> and whoſe Child was buried at <hi>Chelſea.</hi> That about the beginning of <hi>April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>April,</hi> 97.</note> 1697. while Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> lived at her Mother's, there came thither the Lord <hi>Maclesfeld,</hi> Lady <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte Orby,</hi> Lady <hi>Gerard,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Dinah,</hi> whom ſhe knew to be the ſame who uſed to come to Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> with the Mask'd Lady; upon which about Four or Five the next Morning Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> went from her Lodgings without giving any Notice.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant</hi> ſwears, That about a Fortnight after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> 1696. the Gentlewoman who had been delivered of a Female Child in <hi>Queenſtreet,</hi> came to her at Mrs. <hi>Stileman</hi>'s in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> and told her ſhe was <hi>again with Child,</hi> and asked her to leave her Buſineſs, to be with her. That a Fortnight after, a Houſe was taken for her by the Name of <hi>Lee,</hi> in <hi>Fox-Court.</hi> That about the 6th or 7th of <hi>November,</hi> the Gentlewoman came and Lodged there: That ſhe ſaw the Lady who then went by the Name of <hi>Smith,</hi> brought to Bed the 16th of <hi>January,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>or</hi> 7. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1697. 16. <hi>Jan.</hi> 96/7.</note> of a Male-Child; that there were preſent Mrs. <hi>Wright</hi> a Midwife, a Nurſe of her Acquaintance, and <hi>Sarah Redhead:</hi> That the <hi>Monday</hi> following, the Child was Chriſten'd by the Name of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard.</hi> That about Three Weeks after, ſhe went back to Mrs. <hi>Stileman</hi>'s, where they told her
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153188:4"/>the Earl of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> had been to enquire for her; that being ſurprized at it, ſhe went back to the Gentlewoman at <hi>Fox-Court,</hi> whom ſhe informed of that Matter; upon which ſhe burſt out in theſe Words, <hi>I am that Unfortunate Woman the Lady</hi> Maclesfeld. And the ſame Day the Lady being in great Concern, removed from her Lodgings in <hi>Fox-Court,</hi> for fear ſhe ſhould be found by the Lord <hi>Maclesfeld: With whom ſhe ſaid ſhe had not lived for Ten Years; but ſaid ſhe was adviſed by her Friends, if ſhe were found, to give out, That the Lord</hi> Maclesfeld <hi>met with her, and carried her to a Tavern, where he lay with her, and had a Child by her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho the Lady <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> had pretended to Appeal ſo long ſince, as the 24th of <hi>June</hi> laſt, yet her whole buſineſs being to keep off a Sentence; when Publication had paſſed, and Sentence upon the Proofs muſt needs have been given within a Fortnight; then, and not before, ſhe waved her Appeal, and pretended to go on with the Cauſe, foreſeeing that if ſhe ſhould have brought the pretended Grievance before the Delegates, the abſolute Neceſſity ſhe was in of ſeeking De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays would have appeared to ſeveral of the Houſe of Lords, as well as others.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing ſhe did upon the waving her Appeal, was to croſs-examine thoſe Witneſſes whom ſhe knew to be privy to the Principal Facts. As to the Circumſtances of them, ſhe was too cautious to repeat the Enquiry; her chief buſineſs was to hunt out ſome Imputation of Bribery;<note place="margin">6. <hi>Nov.</hi> 97.</note> but their Anſwers to all the Interrogatives are ſo clear and remote from the leaſt Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this, that ſhe cannot by them gain the leaſt ſhadow of a Pretence to cover her Actions.</p>
            <p>On the 12th of <hi>November,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12. <hi>Nov.</hi> 97.</note> and not before, ſhe upon Oath pretends to offer Matter to clear her ſelf; the foundation of her Juſtification ſhe lays in alledging, That the late Earl of <hi>Maclesfeld</hi> turned her out of Doors; but beſides that this is manifeſtly falſe; were it true, every body will certainly do ſo much Juſtice to his Memory, to believe that one of his Humanity, and good Breeding, would not have turned her out of Doors, in the Abſence of his son, without very juſt Cauſe. She admits that the preſent Earl and ſhe have not cohabited together for ſeveral Years, but will have it, That <hi>ſhe was and is a Perſon of a Virtuous and Sober Life and Converſation, and for ſuch ſhe was, and is accounted, reputed, and taken to be.</hi> Whether ſuch is her Reputation, the Earl appeals to the World: but notwithſtanding her Injuring his Father's Memory, as well as Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Family, he cannot but pity her, for endeavouring to juſtify her ſelf by manifeſt Perjury: As to the Obligation which ſhe pretends to have laid upon him by petitioning for his Life, he cannot think (though he ſhould believe a thing of Courſe and Form had the Effect ſhe vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagines) that therefore he ought to ſacrifice the Intereſt of his Family to her Adulteries: However, this Pretence is wholly groundleſs; for there are ſeveral of the Houſe of Lords, to whoſe Interpoſition he gratefully acknowledges that he owes his Life.</p>
            <p>But to her great Misfortune, Mrs. <hi>Pheaſant,</hi> with whom ſhe had lived with ſo much Reſerve, as never to truſt her with the great Secret, of her being the Lady <hi>Maclesfeld,</hi> till her ſudden fear ſurprized her into it, together with Nurſe <hi>Mountaine,</hi> who nurſed the firſt Child, and <hi>Sarah Redhead,</hi> who attended her when by the Name of Madam <hi>Smith,</hi> ſhe was Delivered of the ſecond; all ſaw her at Doctors Commons when ſhe brought in her Allegations: and at the very firſt ſight knew, with full certainty, that ſhe was the Perſon concerning whom they had in Court, ſhe was ſeen to cover her Face for ſome time with her Fan, till adviſed by one of her own Councel to remove it. After all, to this very day, ſhe has pleaded nothing to the Facts of which ſhe had been accuſed in the Earl's Allegation above Seven Months ſince, nor has pleaded any Matter contrary, any otherwiſe, than as ſhe ſwears her ſelf to have lived a virtuous Life: nor would her Proctor declare when he would be ready, as if they wanted time to ſuborn Witneſſes to defeat the Proofs.</p>
            <p>This being his Lordſhip's Caſe, as it ſtood in <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> beſides ſeveral other Particulars of an extraordinary nature which he has in proof; the delays being ſo manifeſt, and as he can prove, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned only to keep the Matter from coming into Parliament; and ſuch opportunity having been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for her to clear her Innocence if ſhe could, and no one ſtep taken towards it; he cannot but hope the Houſe, of which he has the Honour to be a Member, will look upon the Matter to be ſufficiently ripe for that Remedy which nothing but a Parliament can give: All the Relief by a Sentence in <hi>Doctors Commons,</hi> after the moſt artificial and dangerous Delays, being no more than that State of Separation in which they have already long lived. But it is evident, That the Divine Law admits of Second Marriages in ſuch Caſes as his, and that there have been Acts of Parliament for them, as well as for Baſtardizing Spurious Iſſue. And it may further be conſidered, That thoſe Canons which have prohibited Second Marriages in like Caſes, were ſo manifeſtly an effect of the Popiſh Doctrine of the Sacrament of Marriage, and of the Avarice of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> to get Money for diſpenſing with them; that in the Reformation of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws, prepared and intended in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. in purſuance of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. there was expreſs Liberty given by thoſe Canons to marry again; which by virtue of that Act of Parliament, would have become a General Law, or at leaſt have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned one.<note place="margin">Tit. de nuptiis &amp; divortiis, cap. 5.</note> But whatever Objection may be againſt ſuch a General Law, from the Temptation it may give ill People to ſeck groundleſs Diſſolutions of Marriages; yet upon extraordinary Caſes, ſuch as this is; ſuch Relief has been granted; and where it has been denied, either there has not been Satisfaction in the Evidence of the Fact, or the Parties have cohabited, or after the Grounds of Diſſatisfaction have been reconciled: but if in ſuch a concurrence of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as in the Earl's Caſe, he muſt ſtill be thought to have a Wife, and the Children ſhe has had, muſt be looked upon as his, from the Common Preſumption, till contrary Proof, in that they were born within the Four Seas; Beſides that it cannot but be too great an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Women to make an ill Uſe of a Separate Maintenance, which is provided for in moſt Settlements; it would be a moſt unreaſonable Hardſhip upon the Earl of <hi>Maclesfeld,</hi> that the ſtanding Law, which is deſigned to do every man Right, ſhould by the Rigor of the Letter be to him the Cauſe of the greateſt Wrong; and that for his Wife's Fault he ſhould be deprived of the common Privilege of every Freeman in the World, to have an Heir of his own Body to inherit what he poſſeſſes either of Honour or Eſtate: Or that his only Brother ſhould loſe his Claim to both, and have his Birthright ſacrific'd to the Lady <hi>Maclesfeld</hi>'s Looſe Life.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
